Guide to the Curtis Putnam Nettels papers,1917-1981.
Nettels, Curtis Putnam papers, 1917-1981
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Curtis Putnam Nettels papers, 1917-1981.
14-17-1256
Curtis Putnam Nettels, 1898-1981.
3 cubic ft.
Includes correspondence, clippings, congressional voting lists, articles and letters to editors.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
Includes papers relating to political issues.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of American history.
Curtis Putnam Nettels taught American History at Cornell University from 1945-1967. His memberships included the American Historical Association and Phi Beta Kappa.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, clippings, congressional voting lists, articles, letters to editors, and other papers relating to political issues such as the Panama Canal treaties (Feb. 1978-Dec. 1979), the Taiwan Treaty (1979), U.S. isolationism, foreign aid, the Marshall Plan, and other topics; book reviews; articles by Nettels; correspondence with politicians including Robert Dole, Samuel J. Ervin, Gerald R. Ford, William Loeb, George McGovern, Matthew F. McHugh, Edmund Muskie, William Proxmire, Margaret Chase Smith, and John Tunney; other correspondence files, including correspondence with Van Wyck Brooks; autobiographical sketch, "Boyhood Days in a Prairie Town: Memories of Life in Topeka, Kansas, 1905-1917;" statement by Nettels, "The Doctrine of Containment," and a revised edition of the statement; American history bibliography; and other papers of Curtis Putnam Nettels.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Nettels, Curtis Putnam, 1898-1981.; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963.; Dole, Robert J., 1923-; Ervin, Sam J., 1896-; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-; Loeb, William, 1905-; McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-; McHugh, Matthew F. (Matthew Francis), 1938-; Muskie, Edmund S., 1914-; Proxmire, William.; Smith, Margaret Chase, 1897-; Tunney, John.; Panama.
Subjects:
Economic assistance, American.; Politics, Practical.; Neutrality--United States.
Places:
United States--Foreign policy--Taiwan.; United States--Politics and government.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Book reviews, 1927-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Reviews which have appeared in the Wisconsin Magazine of History, English Historical Review, Mississippi Valley Historical Review, New England Quarterly, The Journal of Modern History, American Historical Review
- Book reviews, 1941-1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Reviews which have appeared in the Journal of Southern History, The New England Quarterly, Pennsylvania Magazine of History of Biography, Mississippi Historical Review, Annals of the American Academy, Journal of Economic History, William and Mary Quarterly, Political Science Quarterly, English Historical Review
- Book reviews, 1951-1956; 1958-1962,; 1965,; 1974,; 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Reviews which have appeared in The Chicago Tribune and The Chicago Tribune Magazine of Books; Annals of the American Academy, Pennsylvania History, American Historical Review, Journal of Political Economy, Saturday Review Magazine, New York Times Book Review, New England Quarterly, New York History, The Historian, Presidential Studies Quarterly
- Various book reviews, 1934-1939; 1946,; 1954,; 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Some of Professor Nettel's writings are reviewed, for example: The Money Supply of the American Colonies before 1720, The Roots of American Civilization, and George Washington and American Independence. The reviews were published in newspapers, magazines and professional journals across the United States, Canada and England
- Printed copies of historical writings by Professor Nettels (Box 1, Folder 5)
  1924, 1947-1953, 1960, 1962, 1965
  Two xerox copies and one typescript copy of the Ithaca Journal's 150 year Anniversary section, May 22, 1965. The newspaper includes the article "Pioneer Conditions Prevailed in 1815 ." Two printed copies of "The English Colonies in America, 1607-1763 ;" one typescript letter dated Sept. 19, 1947, and several published reviews
- Correspondence, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Correspondence is of a poltical nature to and from senators, congressmen, and govenors. Some examples are: Robert Dole, Sam J. Ervin, Gerald R. Ford, William Loeb, George McGovern, Margaret Chase Smith, John Tunny
- Articles pertaining to political controversy and thought wirtten by Porfessor Nettels, 1959; 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Letters written to the New York Times, Manchester New Hampshire Union Leader, and the Ithaca Journal. Many of these newspaper clippings are related to letters in folder six
- Foreign Banks and Government Debts, 1975; 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Correspondence, letters to newspapers and printed reports re the issue of foreign ownership of portions of United States banks
- Correspondence, newspaper clippings, congressional voting lists re Panama Canal Treaties, Feb. 1978-Dec. 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Articles and letters written to various newspapers around the country, 1917; 1922-1925,; 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  The topics deal with United States isolationism, Kansas populism, foreign aid, the Marshall Plan, and the North Atlantic Pact
- Correspondence and articles re the Taiwan Treaty, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letters to editors of various newspapers, 1968-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Letters mainly to the New York Times and the Ithaca Journal, and also to professional journals re former and current United States presidents, presidential power, impeachment, Richard Nixon, the United States Constitution, and Ronald Reagan's candidcay and election
- Press conference of New York's Gov. Nelson Rockefeller on Mar. 4, 1969, 1969-1970; 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Also, a bill to deal with college campus disorders, which was made into state law. Act of Apr. 21, 1969
- A - Correspondence with other historians (people actively involved in the field), colleagues, publishers, 1923; 1931-1934,; 1941,; 1951-1953,; 1977,; 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- B - Correspondence with historians, colleagues, publishers, and others, 1928-1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- C - Correspondence, 1924; 1932,; 1936,; 1943,; 1947-1953,; 1960-1966,; 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- D - Correspondence, 1931; 1933,; 1937,; 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- E - Correspondence, 1947-1949; 1956,; 1963-1964,; 1976,; 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- F - Correspondence, 1931-1937; 1947-1952,; 1961,; 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- G - Correspondence, 1939; 1941,; 1962-1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- H - Correspondence, 1922-1924; 1931-1938,; 1944-1953,; 1966-1967,; 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- I - Letter, Mar. 16, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- J - Correspondence, 1932-1941; 1955-1956,; 1975,; 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- K - Correspondence, 1921; 1930-1934,; 1938-1949,; 1955-1956,; 1961-1963,; 1976,; 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- L - Correspondence, 1962; 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Mc - Correspondence, 1951; 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Me - Correspondence, 1925; 1933,; 1939,; 1945,; 1951-1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Mi - Correspondence, 1932-1933; 1937,; 1946,; 1951-1953,; 1957-1959,; 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- N - Correspondence, 1922-1924; 1930-1939,; 1946-1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Articles and letters which have appeared in The Nation, The New Republic, The New York Times
- O - Letters, 1921; 1923,; 1934,; 1938,; 1956,; 1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- P - Correspondence, articles, 1933-1934; 1938-1943,; 1955,; 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Q - Letters, 1974; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- R - Correspondence, 1925; 1931-1934,; 1938-1945,; 1952-1964,; 1968-1969,; 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Sa - Correspondence, 1922-1924; 1931-1933,; 1937-1942,; 1946-1968,; 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Sm - Correspondence, 1934; 1952, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- T - Letters, 1925; 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- V - One copy of a letter and monograph: Benjamin Franklin by Alexander Vianu, Nov. 6, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- W - Correspondence, journal articles, 1929; 1935,; 1943-1944,; 1951,; 1955,; 1958,; 1962,; 1969,; 1972-1981 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Z- Letter, Mar. 26, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Three repreints of published articles: (Box 1, Folder 40)
  1. "A Link in the Chain of Events Leading to American Independence," from the William and Mary Quarterly, Jan. 1946
  2. "The American Doctrine of Containment." 1980 (2 copies)
  3. The Origins of the Union and of the States. Separate from the Proceedings of the Massachusettes Historical Society. Vol. 72, ( 1957-1960 )
- Twenty-six letters from Curtis Nettels to Van Wyck Brooks, the American author, critic, and translator, 1952-1954; 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  The letters deal mainly with American writers and American literature, some political issues and also discussion of Mr. Brook's books. Some examples of his well known books are: The Wine of the Puritans, 1909; America's Coming of Age, 1915; The Ordeal of Mark Twain, 1920; The Pilgrimage of Henry James, 1925; The Life of Emerson, 1932; The Flowering of New England, 1936; New England: Indian Summer, 1940; The World of Washington Irving, 1944; The Confident Years, 1952; The Writer in America, 1953; Helen Keller, Sketch for a Portrait, 1956; Days of the Phoenix, 1957
- Letters, 1952; 1959 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  This folder contains seven photocopies of letters from Van Wyck Brooks to Mr. Nettels. Also, one photocopy of a newspaper clipping written by Curtis Nettels re Van Wyck Brooks
- One seventy-two page typescript manuscript: "Boyhood Days in a Prarie Town, Memories of Life in Topeka, Kansas, 1905-1917 ," by Curtis Nettels (2 copies) (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Students of Curtis Nettels listed in Who's Who in America (Box 1, Folder 44)
- "A Bibliography of Works on American History Published before 1966 " (598 works are listed). Presented by Curtis Nettels. Privately printed, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- "The Doctrine of Containment," by Curtis P. Nettels. Introductory note and article. 9 pages (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Apr. 1941-Sept. 30, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
- Nov. 1947-Dec. 31, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 8-13)
- Jan. 1948-Oct. 31, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 14-18)
- Nov. 1948-Apr. 30, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 19-23)
- May 1949-Dec. 31, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 24-28)
- Jan. 1950-1973 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
- Jan. 1950-1973 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)